in terms of sorta but as sort of an
uppity yeah it's it's Terence it does
that one should understand consciousness
consciousness is to be understood well
no not not intention so the body
complete understanding of consciousness
is rng if you have completely understood
consciousness we do completely remove
the slightest traces of conceit
conceiving craving and so on so that
means you're another hunter so sotapanna
should at least understand like i need
to understand what principle of freedom
from suffering is
in the phone over toothpaste
then if you were to follow the
understanding of the Four Noble Truths
he would carry on into you uploading any
conceiving so like even when you arrive
at things you did in the sutras like
consciousness to be understood non
indicative luminous soul and whatever
the translations are from different
translators that sounds abstract now
because kind of is but even
understanding of such abstract things
can only happen rightly on the basis of
practical application so now when you
think in terms of the consciousness
needs to be understood you don't you
don't want to allow yourself to keep
thinking it in the abstract domain but
you want to see okay so am i conscious
now you asked you saw that because it's
that consciousness that you are
conscious now that's the constant that
needs to be understood but see what if
you approach it our consciousness is
it's not indicative of weirdness
luminous presence whatever you translate
it with it's already in App Store
category that you will be thinking about
at the expense of your present enduring
conscious experience as a whole and
that's why you'll never arrive at that
with consciousness is because that's
just another way of misconceiving it you
start with the idea that's already
affected with with wrong notion of our
consciousnesses so you have to start
like that but you want to ask yourself
now and my conscious right now see if I
ask you now are you conscious where when
you say i Yin when you say that there is
consciousness there what is it it you
refer to me experiencing me so is there
any other way you can know consciousness
under other people exactly because if
you can think of another way it would be
you experiencing you're thinking that
you are conscious all so consciousness
and experience are inseparable
it's not like this consciousness and
there's the experience for the
consciousness you can only discern
consciousness as the presence of the
experience of any kind that's why it's
always the five aggregates it's not four
in one for three and two and two and a
half in two and a half it's far out yet
the heap so it's the conscious heap so
if your experience right here right now
you said that's pretty much your
conscious off do you well what are the
characteristics what would be the
characteristics yield you might want to
describe it mmm so what will be the
characteristics of the consciousness
within that experience as a whole that
you're conscious of [Music]
[Music]
consciousness the unconscious
self-consciousness describing the
consciousness you said well it's the
experience okay what else can you say
about it don't think in terms of the
stuff you read about consciousness yeah
think in terms of right now say I never
heard about consciousness and I come to
you and I ask you can you tell me what
what do you mean by consciousness that I
can relate in my experience right here
right now the ability to think like like for me
it's like that's one of the reasons our
to dust about it because if it's one of
the hardest that I've found to be
pinpointing without trying to put it out
there sort of like a external object so
how can you pinpoint them because they
okay so you can pinpoint or rather you
want to pinpoint but you know you can't
put it as an external object so what
would you be pinpointing then unless
it's an external object that's why it's
so hard for you to understand it because
your idea of it contradict itself -
you're right you can't pinpoint
consciousness because there will be
something you're conscious off so how
can you then describe the consciousness
of something
well you can only describe it on account
of that thing that you're conscious off
so you can only describe consciousness
negatively okay what it is not
consciousness is defined by that which
you are conscious of that's always say
there's six types consciousness
consciousness of the eyes nose mouth ear
body and mind so the site defines the
eye consciousness presence of the sight
means there is consciousness there so
that's the point to see it the problem
is when people think consciousness they
think of this kind of duality like the
world and me I am conscious my mind is
conscious the world is there its
objective subjective is where my
consciousness is but all of that is
already on the basis of experience as a
whole that you have any division that
you might have me in the world subject
object is the result of the first things
arising as a whole within which you can
focus on different aspects so your
consciousness is not more in you than
these banyan roots are quite the
opposite if consciousness is only
defined definable by the sense sense
domains means your consciousness is out
there with the senses not in your head
in your brain or in your mind that's
where there's six consciousness class is
present so to speak and it's not like
one and then they take the place you
have your eyes at the same time when
there is your nose your mouth your body
your intellect so the six domains of
consciousness are always there
obviously you can't attend to all of
them at the same time your attention
will be drawn to one domain more than
the other
let's see now we're talking we're
thinking you're looking at me but at the
back of your mind
there is the consciousness of sound
still enduring why because halfway
through our conversation your attention
can be drawn to sounds or to the end
biting your foot means the the body of
the six layers of consciousness so to
speak for the sixth it's always there
doesn't disappear you can only attend it
or not attend it but either way you can
only do that because it's already there
so that's the point practically speaking
now your consciousness is out there with
that body video sense is not in your
head your attention fits really if you
want to say something's in my head it's
like what you choose to attend on
account of given given the state of
things but even that's it's not really
in your head because you can attempt to
your head
which means where's the consciousness
then your your attention so the point is
to recognize that this gratuitous notion
that consciousness is in me is
completely mistaken because you can you
can start with your two eyes no
conscience is in me oh how do I know
that because I'm experiencing the idea
of inside of me consciousness being
there and I'm conscious of that whole
thing as a whole so that also that
cannot be my consciousness so
consciousness literally the most
accurately you can describe is its
presence of things which means it always
has to be something present and the fact
that it's present means consciousness is
the consciousness and things means
presence of things not I am conscious or
I make the effort to be conscious no I
can make the effort to attend this and
not attend that on account of it all
being already within those sense domains
that are conscious on their own and when
you realize you have six consciousnesses
at the same time you can't take any of
those to be one single unifying owner of
all the senses because which one is it
when there's six rulers who's in charge
when they're all on the equal footing so
the plurality recognition of that within
your experience removes the basis for
gratuitous assumption of that singular
sense of self
but mine this mind is doing a sort of
well mind is the result of it mind as
the result of the fire griots mind is
not consciousness consciousness of the
senses means the mind is there
mine is the result of the six domains of
senses six domain five domains of senses
five domains of consciousness make up
the for the six domain which is the mind
it's not like one two three four five
six it's five and one if they would give
you if you would only to have eye and
eye consciousness and no other sense
whatsoever self reflection would not be possible
self reflection would not be possible
you wouldn't be able to think there will
be no space the ten and so to speak
between these different domains there's
nothing to move on to is nothing to know
what there is no reference point but now
you have reference we have six Ref yeah
five refuges pointed at them in the six
weeks and six in the in regard to ten is
the five the sixth so the mind it them
is the five senses but there will be no
mind without the five senses defining it
so that's the whole point if you are
inclined to think about consciousness or
mind do so read the sutras about it but
you have to do it on the practical you
mustn't do it at the expense of your
present enduring experience as a whole
right here right now because then is
just abstract sort of whatever
proliferating are you feeling anything
about now is there a feeling in do ya
means consciousness has to be there
sighs I mean you want to regard
consciousness in the same level you
regard form in forms because forms are
discernible only because the senses and
that's discernible only because there is
consciousness paired with our senses
yeah that woman's like our consciousness
is out there with the things it's not
like things are conscious but
consciousness is on the same footing as
things you can perceive because that's
why you're perceiving them that's why
they're present because the domain of
consciousness enables it but if you try
to approach consciousness in positive
terms in point it well you can think you
did but that's a contradiction in terms
because that in itself is presence and
you can't explain presence of presence
we can only explain presence of
something and if you say well my pure
presence there is nothing else present
there well then you take your presence
to be an object that is pleasant for you
present it yeah yeah and the exactly the
sixth sense is the mind mind images are
present that to the mind because there
is mind consciousness or consciousness
in regard to the domain of mind and mind
objects damage
but then you can also make it even more
personal you ask yourself okay so why do
I want to understand consciousness cuz
you want to get it right of you why do
you want the right view
so cessation of suffering is valuable to
you yes and where's that suffering which
you wanted to cease are you suffering
hey I've set or agree to what to the
degree that I'm pressured neutrally
right you're not suffering they spin
economy neutral feeling in itself it's
not painful but you're suffering on
account of its presence before whatever
reason so to speak yeah so why would you
then go anywhere else in order to
understand consciousness in order to get
the right view in order to be free from
suffering in order to be free from the
pressure when you have it right there
with you because a believer can you
believe you can what I can look at it
for it and anywhere else like is that a
matter of belief you obviously can
because you you are looking somewhere
else so I'm asking you why would you do
that
so the problem is right here right now
your liability to suffering is a problem
your pressure and the neutral feeling is
a problem pressure of the pool of the
pleasant feeling is a problem pressure
of the resistance to unpleasant feeling
is a problem obviously not all of them
are present at the same time one of them
can only be present which means you are
liable to the others so why would you go
anywhere else if that's a problem why
would you go anywhere else in order to
solve that problem
why don't you just and understand that
that's I mean more often than not when
people want to contemplate you end up
forgetting the most primordial the most
fundamental present enduring reasons
because of which you want to contemplate
and some of these people on this get a
sense of that but then they go too far
the other way ah don't be trying to
understand there is nothing to be
understood just be here now all people
know I must understand but then in the
expense of their attempts of
understanding they abandon here and now
and actually you don't want to do either
or you want to not do both you want to
find the middle so how can I understand
without compromising my here and now but
without also dismissing the the fact
that you must understand the problem
suffering is a problem ignorant is a
problem if it's understood the Buddha
said you'll be free from it so if you
don't want to abandon here and now
doesn't mean you mustn't try to
understand which is when people kind of
mystified their experience by dismissing
the the necessity of clarity because any
notion of clarity that I have is clarity
of abstract thought but there is that
in-between there is the concrete
thinking non-abstract thinking that you
can think and make effort understand on
account of and within the present
enduring things as a whole you wouldn't
have to abandon your present situation
you will not have to ignore it you can't
abandon it
within it but you can ignore it so if
you have a notion of consciousness of
feelings pilot understand it absolutely
great just don't allow that to take you away
just don't allow that to take you away
from present enduring experience as a
whole but then at the same time don't
allow present enduring experience the
whole to make you darling lazy and and
kind of complacent so you don't make the
effort to understand presently viewing
experience at all that's what needs to
be understood while being present so
that's always come back to what is my
current enduring feeling how do I feel
overall neutral but it's painful because
I'm kind of confused in regard to it I
want to be free from it that freedom is
found right there and then within that
relationship of what you feel and pain
you're liable to because of that
pressure and that that that relationship
is the relationship of craving that's
why there is only one root of suffering
craving nothing else doesn't matter how
diverse your suffering can be if there
is suffering present in your experience
of any kind of any extent on any level
it's because craving is present craving
in regard to what you're currently
feeling so the craving is not maintained
anymore by you then feeling will just be
the feeling perception which is the
perception where is the Buddha said in
the scene they'll just be the scene in
the hood just be the head not because
you ignore everything else that's in it
but because you stop misconceiving
anything else that's not in it so
doesn't matter the extent of the sights
the extent of the sound smell taste
touch thoughts you will not miss
conceive it through your craving through
looking elsewhere
so you can still think we can still
think abstractly you can think about
past by the future none of that would be
presently misconceived through resisting
how you feel in regard to it and that
was always a problem not knowing where
the problem is
so trying to solve it resolve it
elsewhere and the problem is with regard
to present enduring feeling that you
have right here right now and your
attitude of resisting it either towards
away or everywhere
you find the pain of the pressures and
then stop resisting the pain of it and
let the pleasure be
so this with the craving that you can
move sort of like look for a direction
rather yeah there has to be a first
motivator so to speak that's what we
meant by craving is to be abandoned by
the means of craving you create to be
free from suffering in the same way that
you're craving it makes you suffer in
the first place but if you then discern
where the actual problem of that is you
can learn how to stop craving stop
feeling the craving craving is not like
a choice you make but it's a result of
the choices you make through craving
they end up maintaining the craving so
yes you have craving to understand
freedom from suffering so out of that
craving you make the effort you do the
suitors you practice sense restraint you
celebrate you keep the precepts all that
is rooted in craving fine there's no
problem with that
but if that's all you do means you're
never gonna look at the domain where the
actual craving is let's say once you
start doing that and then you recognize
okay now I need to see where the craving
is within this experience that's now
restrained within the precepts and so on
then you get to understand that even
your effort to understand consciousness
for example oh is rooted in craving so
it doesn't mean I should not understand
consciousness just means I should not do
it out of clay so how you not do it out
of craving well but first of all not
allowing that craving to take you
elsewhere other than the other than were
that consciousness or whatever aspect
Adama can be understood which is present
enduring experience as a whole because
that sometimes hard to see that oh wait
because it's you know it's good to make
effort to understand the damn it is but
you need to basically shop and make that
effort more accurate because otherwise
you'll end up part of craving to
understand the Dhamma you end up
maintaining your craving because of
which you don't understand the dumb
so yes I won't understand consciousness
or I won't understand feeling what I
want are the same craving first thing is
not to allow that inspiration to do so
to take me anywhere else in think on any
other terms except present enduring
experience as a whole how do you feel
right now
what is my present enduring posture
right now what am I love like the Buddha
said you you you look basically and ask
yourself oh other things in me right
here right now because of which by not
abandoning them I can experience lust in
the future other things right here right
now in me because of which by not
abandoning them I would experience your
will what I would get hindrances or
anything oh are they I don't know well
because of that there are so I need to
know how can I not be liable to these
unwholesome things because of which
craving gets perpetuated so in a kind of
your craving you discerned enough to
stop yourself from going elsewhere
looking elsewhere because of that
craving and you start looking at the
present enduring situation
he's my mind free from greed over
delusion right now he's my mind gripped
with the desire no he's my mind gripped
with irritation and your will no he's my
mind gripped with discontent
no okay now next set of questions can my
mind remain non-infected with desire
would I know how to maintain it so the
desire cannot enter it can my mind
remain about vailable so I will cannot
enter camera mind remain above this
content so this content cannot enter it
and the only way to figure it out too
the only way to accomplish that is to
understand how that is done otherwise
you just wishful thinking just hoping
that okay now I've done something that
resulted in me being currently free from
desire but I have no idea really
directly I have no direct inside knowing
it's because of this so because of that
because I abandoned this and cultivated
that and because you don't know that
that's what desire will come back your
will will come back which means you're
not free
so how do i contemplate that without
losing the current base so what are you
feeling right now
neutral neutral how about now
say so what's happening to that feeling
all this time and dear to have a say in
that endurance did you did you have a
say in its creation
I don't know very painful it's
inconceivable can you tell it to go away
bingo hmm so why do then try to relate
it
however relationshi with it or at
badeley that feeling doesn't even know
about you you don't exist for it
clearly he has its own arising has its
own ceasing has its own domain so what's
the problem
to that side you realize the problem is
that you forget that and when you forget
that you act out of the feelings when
you forget that you will say you cannot
penetrate or enter the feeling would
interfere with it that's when you
activate sensuality act out of ill-will
act out of boredom
so cultivate and rekey really
interrogate yourself and when it becomes
mechanical sit down tighten down the
effort a bit more and then find the new
sets of questions they will bring you
back to the same thing which is watch my
that's my card and body posture they
ever seen it they were saying the
beating heart they're saying things that
occurred you can only sort of squirm and
resist when they're there but even ideas
will make that makes no difference
that's a result with me all over being
affected by those things so maintain the
context they were those present in doing
don't lose the sight of it and like what
I was present enduring in terms of what
you're feeling don't lose the sight of
it and you will not be able to act too
far out of the craving and the less far
you act out the clearer that the whole
nature of acting out becomes treating it
pretty much stop feeding it until it
loses its strength on account of you're
not providing its food and then you can
overpower it and subdue it and tame it
say you want to train a dog first you
make it you do it with Whitley place
clay its hungry dog just eating a lot he
want you understand if he hasn't
listened to you before so you need to be
draw it from its feeding ground because
if it perceives that you can always eat
whenever he wants to eat high ones to
eat it doesn't need you just going to do
it so you restrain it from going to each
one everyone Street then you realize
that the only way you can get food is
through you in which case it better
starts doing what you want to do and it
is I mean I'm using the simile of the
dogs all the time but it's the same in
the suit that's just to other
animals but it's the same principle like
the five senses are the five wild
animals with their respective feeding
grounds monkey crocodile this matter the
point is in order for you to train them
in order for you to make them obey you
your intentions your mind not all the
way around
you need to restrict the extent of free
roaming and then they realize the only
way they can get these things is if they
listen to you and then just sit down and
wait for food because that's the problem
by the words now that they go hungry or
so the problem is that they eat
carelessly everything stealing things
this shouldn't be eating
that's when you keep corner fear at the
back we mind always in that peripheral
context of what is the currently
enduring feeling but mine currently
enduring intentions but I want to do
what for
to what extent it's not it's not
something I must keep this in front of
my mind all the time what the opposite
start doing it rightly you're more and
more space to relax within it but you
need to first subdue the animal and then
do the discomfort of it